Guide to the A. Hollis Edens papers, circa 1850s-1994
Duke University. University Archives
A. Hollis Edens papers circa 1850s-1994
Duke University. University Archives
Edens, A. Hollis, 1901-
9.0 linear feet Extent: approx. 2700 Items
A. Hollis Edens served as President of Duke University from 1949-1960. This collection includes material largely of a personal nature, including correspondence, photographs, printed material, clippings, and scrapbooks. The collection ranges in date from circa 1850s-1994.
UA.03.57.0002
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The A. Hollis Edens Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2011-2012.
Biographical Note
Arthur Hollis Edens was born on February 14, 1901 in Willow Grove, Tennessee. He was the son of Everett C. Edens, a Methodist minister, and Barbara Ellen (Jolly) Edens. He attended Emory University from which he received the degrees of B.Ph. (1930) and M.A. (1938). He also received a Masters of Public Administration degree (1944) and a Ph.D. (1949) from Harvard University. Prior to coming to Duke, Edens worked as a teacher and administrator at the Cumberland Mountain School and Emory University. In 1946, he was named Dean of Administration at Emory and in 1947, he became Vice Chancellor of the University System of Georgia. In 1948, he was appointed associate director of the General Education Board of the Rockefeller Foundation. In November 1948, the trustees of Duke University selected Edens to serve as president of the institution, a post he held until 1960.
After leaving Duke, Edens served as executive director of the Mary Reynolds Babcock Foundation in Winston-Salem, N.C. Edens died in Atlanta, Georgia on August 7, 1968. He was survived by his wife, Mary Kathleen (Russell) Edens and his daughter, Mary Ann (Mrs. Jefferson D. Wingfield, Jr.).
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, speeches, Duke-related material, Emory-related material, clippings, printed material, scrapbooks, and photographs. The material relates not only to Edens' professional career, but also to his family history and to that of his wife. The majority of the collection consists of family photographs, many of which are unidentified and undated.
Subject Headings
Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Emory University -- History -- 20th century; Edens family
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, (9 boxes)
  - Correspondence between Edens and his daughter, Mary Ann, 1943-1948, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: General Education Board, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Edens Dormitory, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Sampling of Sympathy Letters re: Edens' death, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Duke University: Personal, 1948-1975 (Box 1)
  - Ward Pafford File (Box 1)
  - Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange, 1954, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Emory University, 1937-1969 (Box 1)
  - J. D. Wingfield, Jr., and Family (includes correspondence), 1941-1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Genealogy, undated (Box 1)
  - University System of Georgia, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Harvard University, 1943, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Tribute from Emory University, 1968 Sept. 9 (Box 1)
  - Inauguration Materials: Edens, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Resolution and Note of Appreciation from Duke, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Dedication of Edens Residence Hall, 1970 May (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Addresses, 1949-1953 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Addresses, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Addresses, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Addresses, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Addresses, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Addresses, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: Duke Related (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: General (Box 1)
  - Printed Material, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Printed Material, 1950, 1955, 1959, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Press Releases, Inauguration Prayers, and Bio Sketch, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Photographs/Engravings (Box 1)
  - Bible (with family records inside) (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Photographs (cased photographs and 1 rolled panoramic) (Box 4)
  - Photograph Album, 1930-1941 (Box 5)
  - Loose Photographs (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook of Edens' Career, 1937-1948 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook of Edens' Career, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook of Edens' Career, 1949-1951 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook on Mary Ann Edens, 1949-1951 (Box 5)
  - Oversize Clippings (Box 5)
  - Diplomas, Certificates, Oversize Photographs (Box 6)
  - Mary Ann Edens' scrapbook about her trip to Europe, 1958 Apr.-Aug. (Box 9)
  - Photograph Albums (Box 9)
  - Correspondence between Hollis and Kathleen, 1962 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with Robert Durden, 1991, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with Barney Jones, 1992, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Birth Affidavit, 1954, Death Certificate, 1968 for Hollis Edens; Birth Certificate copy, 1969 for Kathleen Edens (Box 9)
  - Marriage Certificate, 1930, Cemetery Deed, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Mary Ann Edens' Nursing Degree and Board Certification, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 9)
  - Alumni Register, 1957, wih Edens family on cover and a larger print of that image (Box 9)
  - Books (Box 7)
    - "A Rebel War Clerk's Diary," vols. 1-2 (Box 7)
    - Bible presented to Mary Ann Edens by Duke University upon her graduation in 1957 (Box 7)
    - Bible belonging to A. Hollis Edens (Box 7)
    - "The Scarlet Letter" (Box 7)
    - "Caesar's Gallic War" (Box 7)
    - "Selections from Cicero" (Box 7)
  - Vinyl Records, 33 1/3 RPM (Box 8)
    - Men's Glee Club with Perry Como, 1955 April 22 (Box 8)
    - Songs by the Chapel Choir (Box 8)
    - Songs by the Men's Glee Club (2 LPs) (Box 8)
    - Edens-Wingfield Wedding at Duke Chapel, 1959 Feb. 14 (Box 8)
    - Mrs. Kennedy's First Young People's Concert by the Transylvania Symphony Orchestra, 1961 Aug. 22 (Box 8)